A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, History of the University, Confidential papers FA913
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, History of the University, Confidential papers
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA913
0.88 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
2 boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
The work of The Institute concentrated on basic research. The hope was that the discoveries might, in the long run, be applied to the public welfare, but the basic purpose was to provide an environment for exploratory original research by individuals under no compulsion to produce immediately useful results.
Scientific work of The Institute was first carried on through grants-in-aid made to researchers in scattered laboratories. This program decreased as the Institute's own laboratories developed. July 1, 1904 temporary quarters were rented at 127 East 50th Street, New York and work began there about Nov. 1, 1904. Those recruited for the first staff were Eugene L. Opie, Samuel J. Meltzer, Hideyo Noguchi and Joshua Edwin Sweet. Added to the staff very shortly were Phoebus Aaron Theodor Levene and John Auer. Alexis Carrel joined The Institute in 1906 and Jacques Loeb in 1910. On June 13, 1907 the Board of Directors voted to establish various classes of association with The Institute. The classes were: Member (for an indefinite period); Associate Member (for five year periods; amended in 1911 Rules to "a term of years); Associate of The Institute; Fellow of The Institute; Scholar of The Institute (which was dropped in the Rules amended 1928). The first Members of The Institute were Simon Flexner, S.J. Meltzer, E.L. Opie, and P.A.T. Levene.
In April 1906 the Central Laboratory with animal house and power house, located on York Avenue and 66th Street were ready for use. Simon Flexner, the first Director of the laboratories had been unanimously elected Director of The Institute on Oct. 25, 1902. However, not until a meeting on Jan. 17, 1920 did the Board make clear its sense that these were two offices, both held by Simon Flexner. The Office of Director of The Institute was clearly added in amended Rules Oct. 18, 1924. Simon Flexner was Director of The Institute and Director of the laboratories until his retirement in 1935. He was succeeded in both offices by Herbert S. Gasser, 1935-1953.
In 1910, at the York Avenue site a Hospital was opened so that the investigations of the Laboratories could be supplemented by the study of certain diseases as they actually occur in man. The Rules for the Scientific Directors as adopted on Jan. 21, 1911, provided that The Institute be comprised of two coordinate departments, Laboratories and Hospital. Rufus Cole was the first Director of the Department of the Hospital and continued in this post until his retirement in 1937 when he was succeeded by Thomas M. Rivers. The Hospital accepted only a limited number of patients, limited further to classes of diseases under study in the Hospital laboratories. The By-Laws of the Corporation provided that The Institute make no charge to persons treated at the Hospital for professional care rendered or for board and lodging. Classes of appointment to the Hospital were Physician, Assistant Physician, Resident Physician, Superintendent and Assistant Superintendent. In 1946 an amendment to the Rules provided that the titles be as follows: Physician-in-Chief to the Hospital; Physician to the Hospital; Assistant Physician to the Hospital; Resident Associate Physician; Senior Assistant Physician; Superintendent of the Hospital; Assistant Superintendent of the Hospital.
In 1914, at a location about three miles from Princeton, N.J. with Theobald Smith as Director, a new Department of Animal Pathology was established. In June 1915 the Rules were amended to make this coordinate with the Departments of Laboratories and Hospital. When Theobald Smith retired in 1930 Carl TenBroeck became Director of the Department which in 1931 was expanded by the appointment of Louis O. Kunkel who headed the new division of plant pathology into the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology.
The Director of each Department was appointed by the Board of Scientific Directors, and the Director of The Institute by the Corporation. In the different departments separate laboratories were organized under the guidance of a Member or Associate Member. The broad divisions of scientific fields varied from time to time in accordance with scientific developments and the interests of the Members, but always with consultation, approval and direction of the Board of Scientific Directors.
In 1953, after the retirement of Herbert S. Gasser, an extensive reorganization was undertaken. Thomas M. Rivers, who served for two years as Vice-President of the Corporation and at the same time, Director of the Laboratories, Director of the Department of the Hospital and Physician-in-Chief to the Hospital retired in 1955. The position of Director of The Institute was abolished and also the organization into departments.
On and after November 19, 1954 when the Charter of the Corporation was amended so that the Corporation became part of the University of the State of New York The Institute had the power to confer degrees. On June 27, 1958 by amendment to the Charter the corporate name was changed to The Rockefeller Institute and on May 27, 1965 the Charter of The Institute was amended in its entirety and the name changed to The Rockefeller University.
The University is organized into laboratories, each headed by one or two senior scientists rather than into categorical departments. The scientific work of the laboratories is under the direction of the President.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Box 1 Former Classification: I 417.
Box 2 Former Classification: I 417-1.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research.
Custodial History
Box 1 was collected by the Business Manager and arranged because of the historical value. They were labeled confidential and were obviously considered of inflammatory nature (possibly) or private information. None of these attitudes appear to be valid any longer.
Box 2 was placed in a safe in the Bursar's office which later became Comptroller's office or Accounting Office. Other papers were added periodically. In March of 1980 Mr. Lyons turned them over to the Archives. Though they may, at one time, have been considered confidential that is no longer accurate, but does serve for an indentifying label. In some instances the papers are duplicate of items in other holdings.
Arrangement
Arranged in alphabetical order by subject; then in chronological order within subject.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Box 2: Date received or inventoried: April, 1980.
Medical sciences; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Medical research; Operations management; Biology -- Research; Medical education; Life sciences; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Greene, Jerome D.; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University
- Campbell, Edith, 1920 October 6-November 1
  Related Materials
  see under Flexner, Simon.
- Charter, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Copies of petition to Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York with covering correspondence on application to become a degree granting institution.
- Connolly, Bernard, 1926 April 5-1927 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Items covering gas stove explosion, death of Bernard Connolly and settlement and releases from Patrick Connolly running to RIMR.
- Couche, Anna
  see under Oxygen Chamber.
- Egley, Viola Gray Estate
  See under Reynolds, Emily E.
- Endownent, see under
  - Rockefeller, John D., 1908 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rockefeller, John D., 1910 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rockefeller, John D., 1910 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Flexner, S., 1920 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rockefeller, John D., 1920 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rockefeller, John D., 1920 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Flexner, S., 1921 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rockefeller, John D., 1921 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rockefeller, John D., 1926 June 3-1928 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rockefeller, John D., 1948 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Flexner, Simon (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Edith Campbell (Publications Division - in self defense), 1920 October 26-November 1
  - Memorandum of Trustees. meeting Hot Springs, Va. re need for definite and generous endowment for RIMR, 1920 April 27; draft and typescript
  - Letters between P.A.T. Levene and Lillia Trask (handled through Simon Flexner), 1920 January 9-1921 June 16
  - Letters and notes (handwritten) with P.A.T. Levene on budget matters about which he was most unhappy, 1920 May
  - Covering letter from L.G. Myers listing gift of additional securities to RIMR from John D. Rockefeller, 1921 April 14
  - From Edwin R. Embree (Peking Medical College) and telegram from John D. Rockefeller in regard to F.C. McLean, 1921 September 12-19
  - 15 letters from Rufus Cole and James B. Murphy expressing satisfaction with X-Ray Department, 1921 December 12
  - Simon Flexner Cremation Certificate with notes from Peyton Rous (May 8, 1949; April 20, 1958; January 31, 1961 regarding the ashes of Dr. and Mrs. S. Flexner, 1946 May 3
- Gasser, Herbert S. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Copy of letter to A.N. Richards, Committee on MEDICAL RESEARCH, explaining principles to be followed in planning for support of scientific research, 1945 October 11
- Gates, Frederick Taylor and Frederick Lamont (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gates, Frederick Taylor
    - Copy of letter written to Wm. Osier expressing admiration and appreciation and inspiration provided in the reading of "Principles and Practice of Medicine" and signed reply dated March 5, 1920, 1902 March 4
    - Letter to Simon Flexner enclosing the above 1915 December 20 Two copies, one retyped after corrections of letter to Starr J. Murphy telling of Gates recollections of the early thinking behind the establishment of RIMR until the time when Mr. Murphy became involved in the planning, 192[?] December 28
    - Conference. Extract of letter from F.T. Gates to John D. Rockefeller relating to policy for selection of Institute Board Members as expressed at conference, 1926 December 17
  - Gates, Frederick Lamont
    - Copy of Address read to Municipal Club of Brooklyn on the story of the Rockefeller Institute, 1927 November 22
- Gelarie, Arnold J. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notebook, 1914 January 19-April 1
  - Letters to Jacques Loeb, 1914 June 30 1914 August 25
- Greene, Jerome D.
  See under James, Henry. Box 1, Folder 9.
- Herter, Christian Archibald (Box 1, Folder 7A-7E)
  Custodial History note
  This entire file was turned over to Peyton Rous by Polly Herter (Mrs. C. di Tough) [Note: Mrs. M.D. Herter Norton Crena de Iongh.] when Herter-Dakin home (Edgehill) in Scarborough, N.Y. was dismantled after H.D. Dakin's death. Deposited at the Institute 1953 June 23.
  - Letters from Simon Flexner to Christian Herter and Susan Herter, 1902-1910
  - Letters from Helen Flexner
  - Dictated notes on talks with Theobald Smith, James Ford Rhodes, Charles Eliot and Robert Koch
  - Letters, The letters have penciled notes and numbers (the numbering is not in strict chronological order); the markings are unsigned and undated. (Box 1, Folder 7A-7E)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 8 November; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, "Thursday"; 2 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1902 December 11; 3 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1902 January 6 1902 January 8 1902 January 12; 4 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1903 November 21; 5 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1906 June 28; 6 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1906 August 30; 7 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1906 September 24; 8 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1906 September 24; 9 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1907 February 17; 10 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1907 June 30; 11 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
    - Christian Herter to Simon Flexner, 1907 August 19; 12 (Box 1, Box 7b)
    - Christian Herter to Simon Flexner, 1907 September 7; 13 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
    - Christian Herter to Simon Flexner, 1907 September 23; 14 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, "Tuesday PM"; 15 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Christian Herter to Simon Flexner, 1908 June 13; 16 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1908 June 18; 17 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1908 July 19; 18 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1908 July 30; 19 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1908 August 22; 20 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Christian Herter to Simon Flexner, 1908 August 20; 21 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1908 August 28; 22 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1908 August 25; 23 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Christian Herter to Simon Flexner, 1908 September 17; 24 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1909 July 5; 25 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1909 July 17; 26 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Christian Herter, 1909 August 30; 27 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Christian Herter to Simon Flexner, 1909 January 7; 28 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Susan Herter, 1909 September 7; 29 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
    - Simon Flexner to Susan Herter, 1913 August 3; 30 (Box 1, Folder 7c)
      with copy of F. Knoop to Simon Flexner 16 Jul 1913.
    - Helen Flexner to Christian Herter, 1907 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Folder number is 7d (An Archivists' Toolkit bug is preventing this folder number to be entered as such).
    - Helen Flexner to Christian Herter, 22 July (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Helen Flexner to Christian Herter, 28 September (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Helen Flexner to Susan Herter, 31 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Manuscripts (Box 1, Folder 7e)
      - "Notes on a conversation with Dr. Theobald Smith at Seal Harbor, 1905 September 6 (Box 1, Folder 7e)
      - "Notes on a conversation with Mr. Charles W. Elliot at Seal Harbor, 1907 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 7e)
      - "Notes on a conversation with Robert Koch" [University Club], 1908 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 7e)
      - "Notes on a conversation with Mr. John Ford Rhodes at Seal Harbor, 1907 Summer (Box 1, Folder 7e)
- Hospital (Box 1, Folder 8 and 8A)
  - Compiled summary of hospital history to date Notes on plans for a Research Hospital to the affiliated with the Research Laboratories of the Rockefeller Institute (may be part of T.M. Prudden plans), 1929 October
  - J.D. Rockefeller, Jr. to L. Emmett Holt that father authorizes preparation of a plan for an affiliated hospital which he will consider 1907 June 13 Report of Committee on Hospital presented by Christian Herter at meeting of Board of Scientific Directors. Tentatively approved, 1907 February 28
  - Letter from Christian Herter to L. Emmett Holt with outline of plan for the Hospital, 1907 June 27
  - letter from Starr J. Murphy to Christian Herter regarding drafts to be made on General Education Board for Hospital construction (copy), 1908 June 24
  - letter from Christian Herter to Simon Flexner enclosing copy of letter from Starr J. Murphy regarding early conveyance of land for Hospital, 1908 June 27
  - letter from Christian Herter to Simon Flexner regarding use of land abutting Hospital as playground, also includes possible role in Hospital organization for Christian Herter and approval of choice of Rufus Cole as Hospital Director, 1908 August 20
  - Correspondence between Christian Herter and Simon Flexner regarding Hospital, 1908 August 22-September 9
  - Correspondence between Christian Herter and Starr J. Murphy regarding cost to Institute of land for the Hospital, 1908 September 9-11
  - Suggestions in regard to organization of the Hospital of the Rockefeller Institute by Rufus Cole, 1908 December; 16 pp.
    See Folder 8a for photocopy.
  - Letter from Christian Herter to Simon Flexner regarding place on Hospital staff for Foster, 1909 June 25
  - Letter to Simon Flexner from R. Cole written after October 14 meeting of Board of Scientific Directors on question of relationship between Hospital staff and Department of Laboratories staff in research matters See Folder 8a for photocopy, 1911 (?) October 14
  - Letter from Theobald Smith to R. Cole on Cole's letter of October 14, 1911, 1911 December 5
- James, Henry, [Photocopies] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Jerome Greene to H.S. Gasser recalling visit to Institute of Henry James, author with Henry James, Manager, 1948 February 20
  - Letter from Peyton Rous with recollections of Henry James visit, 1948 April 1
  - Copy of letter from Homer Swift with recollections of Henry James' visit, 1948 April 21
- Lavoisier portrait
  See under Rockefeller 1927 Apr. 30, Box 1, Folder 16.
- Loeb, Jacques (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - deed of gift to RIMR of scientific monographs and papers, 1924 April 24
  - correspondence from Leo Loeb regarding Memorial Plaque, 1959 July-September
  - see also under Gelarie, Arnold J.
- Noguchi, Hideyo, 1948 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Agreement of Purchase and Trust agreement with Woodlawn Cemetery for graves of Hideyo Noguchi and wife Mary.
- Oxygen Chamber fire (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Report of fire in Oxygen Chamber. Patient Anna Couche died., 1922 November 17
    Includes signed statements and photographs.
- Paresis cure (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Copy from McClure, received from Wade H. Brown, also original copy as written by Ruby A. Black.
- Peking Union Medical College, 1921 September 12-19
  See under Flexner, Simon. Box 1, Folder 3.
- Pestrecov, Konstantin, 1937 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Release in consideration of $562.50.
- Property, gift of, 1927 November 15
  See under Rockefeller, John D. Box 1, Folder 16.
- Reynolds, Emily E., 1937 November (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Notorized statements in Viola Gray Egley Estate.
- Richards, A.N.
  See under Gasser, Herbert S. Box 1, Folder 4.
- Rockefeller, John D. and John D., Jr. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - William H. Welch to L. Emmett Holt covering letter with copy of letter to JDR, Jr. 1908 May 30 handwritten copy of letter William H. Welch to JDR, Jr. acknowledging with gratitude news of father's provision for land and construction of hospital affiliated with RIMR
  - Typescript copy of letter from William H. Welch to JDR, Jr. in thanks for father's endowment of $3,820,000 on to RIMR at agreement on plan of reorganization, 1910 October 17
  - Letter JDR, Jr. to W.H. Welch acknowledging letter of October 17, 1910 October 28
  - Copy of letter from W.H. Welch to JDR for additional endowment and great generosity making RIMR a reality, 1920 February 28
  - Copy of letter listing securities added to Institute endowment, 1920 December 15
  - Copy of letter from JDR to RIMR additional endowment, 1921 April 5
  - copy letter from W.H. Welch to JDR inapreciation of latest endowment at par value of $5,000,000, 1921 May 10
  - JDR, Jr. to Simon Flexner presenting portrait of Lavoisier and wife by David to RIMR, 1927 April 30
  - 1926 June 3-1928 October 24
    Collection of notes from Board of Trustees meeting where S. Flexner presented report "Development of the first Twenty Years of The Rockefeller Institute and an Outlook for future Growth" Notes of meeting of Scientific Directors 1926 June 5 and correspondence between F.T. Gates, Thomas Debevoise, Simon Flexner, JDR, Jr. and Bertram Cutler involving $20,000,000 pledge made by JDR, Jr. but fulfilled by gift from JDR, Sr.
  - Copy of letter from W.H. Welch to JDR, Jr. expressing gratification on his becoming president of the Corporation and gratitude of Board for gift of property. 1929 November 20 reply from JDR, Jr., 1929 November 15
  - letter from JDR, Jr. establishing trust fund with interest payments to be made to RIMR over a period of 13 years until 1960. Acceptance letter from Trustees dated 1949 October 28. Release running to Chase Bank dated 1952 June 18 and 1952 accounting, 1948 June 16
  - Letter to Herbert Gasser from JDR, Jr. asking he not be renominated at expiration of term as President of Corporation in 1950. Letter honoring JDR, Jr. signed by all Members of the Board 1950 October 27 (with photographic copy) and acknowledgement 1951 January 19 from JDR, Jr. with photographic copy, 1950 April 17
- Rous, Peyton
  Related Archival Materials note
  See under Flexner, Simon, Box 1, Folder 3. See under James, Henry, Box 1, Folder 9.
- Schermerhorn farm house
  See under Tompkins 1920-1923, Box 1, Folder 18.
- Taxation, 1932 October 25-November 11 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Correspondence with Commissioner of Internal Revenue and affidavit on which Treasury Dept. granted tax exempt status to the Institute.
- Tompkins, A.B., 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence and water color sent as gift to owners of Schermerhorn farm house
- Treasurer, 1921 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Letter from L.G. Myers estimating income for 1921-1922.
- Tryparsamide
  see under Paresis cure. Box 1, Folder 13.
- Anti-vivisection, 1910 January (Box 2, Folder 1)
  A collection of depositions mainly as of January 1910 in response to an attack on RIMR charging cruelty in animal experimentation.
- Bank certification. Copy of certification of Board vote on Bank choice, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Bermuda leases, 1920 1930 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Bursar's Office, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Job descriptions for personnel in Bursar's Office.
- Charter/By-Laws (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Copy of original certification
  - Copy of act to amend charter; became law 1908 (creates Board of Trustees) 1910 May 18 Starr J. Murphy to S. Flexner enclosing first draft of By-Laws for reorganization
  - 2nd copy of draft
  - Copy of 2nd draft
  - 2 copies of 3rd draft
  - Letter L. Emmett Holt to S. Flexner enclosing 1910 June 10 letter from S.J. Murphy enclosing reorganization rules, 1910 October 25
  - Copy typescript of original By-Laws with amendments, 1911 January 21
    Holograph notation "These by-laws were replaced by the "Rules" of the Board of Scientific Directors adopted Jan. 21, 1911" JDG.
  - Copy typescript of newly accepted By Laws
  - Copy of consent form of amended By Laws
  - Amends Art. V sec. 1 and Art. V sec. 3
  - Copy of Memorandum of Agreement, 1910 October 15
  - Endowment increased by $3,820,000 with reorganization
- Clyde Farm in New Jersey (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Record of purchase and. history 1907-1908, contracts for certain buildings on the farm
  - Lease with Dominick Nepote, 1916
  - Agreement of sale with Moses and Isaac Rubin, 1919
- Endowments (property), mainly copies (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sale agreement JDR and wife Laura to RIMR, 1904 July 7
  - Indenture for the land within the bed of 65th Street between Ave. A and Exterior Street, 1912 July 18
    1914 Jan. 24 Copy letter JDR to RIMR trustees. Gift of $2,550,000 to pay for land, building and equipment and additional endowment.